PRAKASH LAMICHHANE

Research Officer/Data Ananlyst/Ecologist

Email: forester.prakash@gmail.com | Phone: +977-9845228896 | GitHub: foresterprakash | LinkedIn: Prakash-Lamichhane | ORCID: 0000-0002-0355-0222

About Myself

I am Prakash Lamichhane, a Research Officer, Data Analyst, and Ecologist with a strong educational background in Forestry and Landscape Ecology. My career spans practical experience in forest management and carbon monitoring, driven by a passion for climate science and environmental conservation efforts. I had a significant growth on data analysis and statistical application in any sector data with mastering in MS Excel and R programming in recent years. I am particularly interested in advancing my academic growth in data science and statistical analysis using R programming. I am looking forward to learn from an academic environment to develop data driven approaches to understand the impact of natural disaster on people and ecosystem. Specifically, my research interest encompasses developing an ecosystem service framework linking cultural heritage and promoting disaster resilient communities.



Education

Duration	Course	University	Country
2017 - 2019	M.Sc. Landscape Ecology and Nature Conservation	University of Greifswald	Germany
2010 - 2013	B.Sc. Forestry	Tribhuvan University	Nepal
2007 - 2009	Technical Level in Forestry (I.Sc.)	Tribhuvan University	Nepal

Work Experiences

Year	Affiliation
2017 - 2019	M.Sc. Landscape Ecology and Nature Conservation, Greifswald University
2019 - 2023	Assistant Research Officer, Forest Survey and Carbon Monitoring Section under FRTC
2023 - Present	Research Officer, Climate Change Management Division, MOFE
Part-time	Lecturer, Natural Resource Economics, Kathmandu Forestry College

Major Skills

- National Forest data analysis and Reporting
- Mastering MS. Excel and R programming
- Carbon accounting and MRV process
- Uncertainty Estimation and Sensitivity Analysis
- Data Science with Python
- GIS Tools (QGIS, ARCGIS, Google Earth Engine etc.)
- Integrated Development Environments (IDEs)(i.e., R Studio, VS code, Pycharm, Jupyter Notebook, Collect Earth Online etc.).

Major Job-Related Trainings as Trainee

D	D. W.L. I	<u> </u>	D. C.
Duration	Entitled	Organizers	Reference
23-27 May, 2022	Training on Unbiased Area Estimation and Uncertainty Estimation for Forest Activity Data	USAID,USFS,SilvaCarbon	Crystal Westespad
22- 26 August, 2022	Development of National Landcover Monitoring System for Nepal	International Center for Integrated Mountain Development (ICIMOD) SERVIR-HKH initiative	kabir Uddin
10 October - 11 November, 2022	On the Job training on Forest Carbon Stock Measurement using Earth Observation Data	International Center for Integrated Mountain Development (ICIMOD) SERVIR-HKH initiative	Rajesh Bahadur Thapa
12 May - 13 August 2023	Data Science with Python	Broadways Infosys Pvt.Ltd.	Uttam Adhikari
21- 25 January 2024	FCPF and ART TREES: Technical Training Workshop on REDD+ Emission Reduction Measurement, Reporting and Verification (30hours)	REDD + Implemmentation center, Silva Carbon, FCPF, The World Bank Group Nepal	German Obando - Vargas
22-26 July 2024	Earth Observation (LiDAR and GEDI) for forest carbonstocks monitoring in Nepal	ICIMOD, FRTC, Silva Carbon	Rajesh Bahadur Thapa and Tim Devereux
19 Aug - 6 September 2024	Climate Action and Support Transparency Training(CASTT) Programme on GHGs in Seoul,Republic of Korea	UNFCCC and Green House Gas Inventory and Research Center, South Korea	Jeong Eunhae,President, GIR Korea

Major Job-Related Trainings as Trainer

Duration	Entitled	Organization
Regular From 2022 14 - 21 Aug, 2023	MS Excel and R Programming Trainer in Training on Python Programming	Broadways Infosys Forest Research and TRaining Center
26 Sept - 5 Oct, 2023	Statistical Data Analysis and Forest Mapping	Forest Research and Training Center
4-13 Feb, 2024	Enhancing Capacity on R Programming for Data Analysis and Carbon Accounting	REDD+ Implementation center

Workshop and Seminar

- 1. Cross Country knowledge Exchange on REDD plus program in Cambodia dated from 12/06/2022 to 19/06/2022 Phnom Penn, Siem Reip and Koh Kong province of Cambodia (ORAL PRESENTATION)
- 2. South-South Knowledge Exchange on Measurement, Monitoring, Reporting and Verification systems, FCPF CF ERPA Implementation dated from 12/12/2022 18/12/2022 Maputo, Mozambique.
- 3. Hands-on training workshop on transitioning to the ETF, including the preparation of the Biennial Transparency Report for Asia Region dated from 12/03/2024 to 15/03/2024 Singapore.
- 4. UN Climate Conference Bonn, Germany dated from 03/06/2024 to 09/06/2024

Research Experience

- 1. Preparation of National Landcover monitoring System (NLCMS) using RandomForestClassifier.
- 2. FRTC, 2020, A study of Opportunities and Constraints for Development of Private forestry Model in Mid-Hill Region of Nepal (A case study from Kavre and Kaski district of Nepal), Forest Research and Training Centre (FRTC), Babarmahal, Kathmandu, Nepal. Unpublished
- 3. Preparation of Regional and National Forest Resource assessment (Involvement in field data collection, data analysis and report writing).
- 4. Involvement in generating activity data and emission factors for national emission reduction report for MRV purpose in coordination with FCPF and World Bank.

Publications

- 1. Aryal, S., Paudel, P., Bolakhe, S., Mahatara, D., & Lamichhane, P. (2022). Evaluation of error and efficiency on tree height measurement using Abney's level, Rangefinder and Vertex IV. *Indian Journal of Forestry*, 45(1), 1–8. DOI
- 2. Parajuli, A., Gautam, A. P., Sharma, S., Lamichhane, P., Sharma, G., Bist, B. S., Aryal, U., & Basnet, R. (2022). A Strategy for involving community forest managers in effective forest fire management in Nepal. *Banko Janakari*, 32(1), 41–51. DOI
- 3. Subedi, B., Lamichhane, P., Magar, L. K., & Subedi, T. (2022). Aboveground carbon stocks and sequestration rates of forests under different management regimes in Churia region of Nepal. *Banko Janakari*, 32(1), 15–24. DOI
- 4. Gautam, G. P., Aryal, R. R., & Lamichhane, P. (2018). Restoration of degraded land through Moso bamboo (Phyllostachys pubescens) plantation in the Mid-hills of Nepal. *Banko Janakari*, 150–153. DOI
- 5. Dhakal, R., et al. (2023). Developing Stem Taper of Shorea Robusta in the Far-Western Terai of Nepal. Banko Janakari, 33(2), 3–10. DOI

References

Referee 1	Referee 2	Referee 3
Shiva Khanal PhD	Shes Kanta Bhandari PhD	Buddi Sagar Poudel, PhD
Western Sydney University, Australia	University of Western Australia	Charles Sturt University, Australia
Under Secretary (Tech.), Climate	Assistant Professor, Institute of	Joint Secretary, Climate Change
Change Management Division (CCMD)	Forestry, Tribhuvan University	Management Division (CCMD)
Ministry of Forests and Environment,	Research Interests: Forest	Ministry of Forests and Environment,
Kathmandu, Nepal	Biometrics, Forest Growth and Yield Modelling, Individual-based Modelling, Forest Inventory	Kathmandu, Nepal
Google Scholar: Shiva Khanal	Google Scholar: Shes Kanta Bhandari	ResearchGate: Buddi Sagar Poudel
Email: khanalshiva1@gmail.com	Email: shes.bhandari@pc.tu.edu.np	Email: buddi.poudel@gmail.com, buddhi.poudel@nepal.gov.np
Phone: (+977) 9841492155	Phone: (+977) 9765631067	Phone: (+977) 9841460874